- Previously on Gotham...
- Everybody,
raise your glasses to the killer
of Jeremiah Valeska.
(cheering)
A lead on a guy selling RPGs.
Get out of here, Barbara.
(gunshot)
Eduardo?
Nice shot, right?
Tell me what you did!
I put a chip in your brain.
Better talk, now.
A contract came along.
A contract from who?
(beeps)
Walker wants Ed
Nygma taken out now.
Walker was behind this?
She's been controlling
Nygma the whole time?
- (gasps)
- Ouch.
Stitches still sore, huh?
I told you I had to let
Selina thrust the knife
into my flesh at least once.
(beeps)
You know Jim Gordon.
You know this city.
Find him. And kill him.
(panting)
(gunfire)
(grunts)
Your chances of survival
are astronomically low, James.
Continuing to
run is ill-advised.
(door opens)
(thudding)
(whirring)
♪♪
Hope you're well rested, Edward.
We have a lot of
work ahead of us.
(sighs)
Edward? (chuckles)
(sniffing)
Edward, what is it?
Is someone down there, boy?
(Edward whimpers)
MAGPIE: ♪ Cash
and jewels aplenty ♪
♪ Sparkle in the sky ♪
♪ Five and ten and 20 ♪
♪ Time to say bye-bye. ♪
Ooh, pretty, pretty.
I'll call you
Charlotte. (giggles)
Ooh, you're a handsome
devil. What's your name?
Oswald Cobblepot.
But I'm guessing
you already knew that.
Stop!
Penguin. Didn't think
you'd miss a couple things.
Couple things go
missing all the time.
How did you know
about this place?
All of the thieves
I used are dead.
Yep, yep.
Was on a job.
Someone got there first.
Followed them back here.
Saw you. Bang, bang.
Then you know what is in store.
I do hope whatever you came
here for was worth your life.
(both laugh)
The Russifer Diamond.
Not Russifer. Charlotte.
What's in your other hand?
Wait, how did you...
(groans)
Bye-bye.
(panting)
Who the hell was that?
(grunts) Oh, God...
Oh! (panting)
Oh, God. It happened
again, didn't it?
What did I do?
You tried to kill me.
Oh. Is that all?
I need answers, Ed.
I know Walker gave the
orders to destroy Haven
and the supply helicopter.
What is she planning next?
I don't know.
Jim, I don't remember
anything once I go under.
You're bleeding.
You have to let me go.
I'm not responsible for this.
That chip in your head
could be evidence.
So unless you
want me to rip it out,
- you're coming
with me.
- Okay.
(grunts)
(gunfire in distance)
(indistinct chatter)
ALFRED: Bruce.
There you are.
So, go on, then.
How'd it go with Selina?
Oh, dear.
Well, I am sorry, Master Bruce,
but perhaps it's for the best.
Maybe. That's not why I
called you here. You see this?
Yeah, I know, right?
Looks like Captain Gordon's
finally getting the help this
city so desperately needs.
Is he?
What the people desperately
need is food and medicine.
Not just more guns.
What is it?
No, it's just this unit.
Their motto is "Born of Blood."
You know them?
Yeah, by reputation only.
They're a horrible
bunch of bastards.
They specialize in military
coups, assassinations.
They're certainly
not the vanguard
for humanitarian relief.
Excuse me.
When's the supply
shipment gonna be here?
Supplies?
These people are
desperate for food,
clean water, medicine.
Oh, yeah. It's on its way.
Where's Captain Gordon?
We lost sight of Gordon.
But don't worry. Eduardo's out
there looking for him right now.
Unless you know
where we might find him?
Logically, he'd come here.
Unless there's
some reason he can't.
Tell you what, kiddo.
I'm gonna find you and your
friend a quiet place in the back
where you can wait for Gordon.
Ah, don't you
worry about it, mate.
We'll just catch
up with him later.
I insist.
We need to find Jim.
So the government is behind
Haven and the supply helicopter,
and they did it with a
chip in this one's head?
Is that really
the craziest thing
you've ever heard, Barbara?
Bruce hit me up on the radio
a little while ago,
looking for you.
Said things are
amiss in the GCPD.
I'll reach out, see if we can
meet up somewhere safe.
Can you pull in some of your
people, see if they can help?
No. I need them
guarding my territory.
But you have me.
And me.
I don't trust you.
With or without that
chip in your head.
Jim.
They used me as a pawn
to murder innocent people.
They messed with my brain.
The thing that I
want is revenge.
How do I know that
chip can't be reactivated?
Well, when you found
me at Strange's lab,
he was fixing it after a...
car battery mishap...
I-It's safe to say that I
think you shorted it out.
Let me look at that.
- What?
- Your neck.
That's gonna need
stitches. I have a first aid kit.
I need to keep moving.
Just name your fee.
Can't I just want to help?
Not you, not usually.
Friend of mine
just tried to kill me.
I don't want anyone
else waiting for an excuse
- to stab me in the back.
- I gave you
Gerry the Jerkwad,
and I'm letting you
hide out in my club.
If I wanted to betray you, I
would have done it earlier.
So, where's that first aid kit?
Gonna make myself useful.
What's it gonna take
for you to trust me?
After everything you've
done, I honestly don't know.
EDUARDO: I'd listen to her, Jim.
I hear trust is in short supply.
EDUARDO: You forget
your PSYOPS training, Jim?
Lesson one: when
a person is in trouble,
they go to a familiar place.
Your ex-fiancée's bar was
just a stone's throw away,
so it's nice to finally
meet you, Barbara.
Screw you.
Hmm.
It seems you've lost your tail.
You mean the psychopath
you ordered to kill me?
You had your chance.
It could have been
like old times, buddy.
You, me, together,
making the world a better place.
- By murdering civilians?
- Civilians?
This hellhole is infested
with criminals and terrorists.
Sometimes you just have
to clean house, you know?
I won't let you.
It's not your call, Jim.
(guns clicking)
I'm not dead yet.
James Gordon, I've
been ordered to kill you.
Well, looks like you
haven't lost that tail after all.
(straining): If I die,
you'll never get the evidence!
Stand down.
I have evidence that you
and Walker are behind Haven.
If I die, it gets out
to the entire country.
It's time to make a deal.
You don't have any evidence.
Is that a risk you're
willing to take?
It is.
Nygma, kill them both.
(bell tolling in distance)
(screaming)
(door closes)
Bad time?
(sighs) What do you want?
Depends.
What did they want?
Oh. A shot at me.
I killed Jeremiah Valeska.
(laughs softly)
So the rumors are true.
Yeah.
And now, every scumbag in
town wants to take me down
to make a name for themselves.
So I got to find a new squat.
How about, in exchange
for helping me find someone,
I let you crash in my citadel?
It's seen better days, but...
(laughs): then again, right?
Who?
A miscreant I caught in
the act of stealing from me.
She was going to
replace the stolen item
with an exact replica, except
the replica was a bomb.
- (chuckles)
- Ring any bells?
White hair, feathered collar,
kind of of resembles
a goth chicken?
You do know her.
(chuckles)
She goes by the name Magpie.
What'd she steal?
The Russifer Diamond.
What makes you
think I would help you
after you killed Tabitha
in cold blood?
Because you believe
in an eye for an eye.
Hard as it may be to swallow,
Tabitha made her bed
when she killed my mother.
Tell you what.
I will help you
if I get to keep the diamond.
(laughs)
What?
Not a chance.
Ha, ha, ha. Then
you'll never find her.
And every person in
Gotham will think it's okay
to steal from Penguin.
Is that what you want?
You know me too well.
Fine.
Good.
- What happened?
- EDUARDO: I want
every soldier
in the field looking
for Jim Gordon.
Sir, we maxed out
the holding cells.
We may need to keep men
here to control the overflow.
Ethan, Sumiko.
We're moving to phase two.
(grunts)
What in the hell's going on?
Listen up.
I am not here to play nice.
I am not here to
hold anyone's hand.
I am here on a simple mission.
Any questions about
the nature of that mission?
Are you insane? You
can't just execute people.
Do not question me.
This is the mission.
If you don't like it,
you'll be locked up,
you'll remain locked up,
until we purge the
criminal element
from the streets of Gotham.
Sir, Secretary
Walker's on the radio.
(cell door closes)
We've moved on to phase
two, but we've lost track
of Gordon and Nygma.
I think Gordon found
a way to fry the chip.
WALKER: We can't have Nygma
in the wind with all that
evidence in his head.
Just trust me.
Once we find them...
Don't bother.
I have an idea that will bring
Jim Gordon and Nygma to us.
Thanks for getting
everyone here.
And for the Wayne R and D.
Are you sure about including
Barbara Kean and Ed Nygma?
War makes for
strange bedfellows.
It's good to have a
friend nearby, Bruce.
Ow! Would you be careful?
If you'll stop moving,
this will go a lot faster.
NYGMA: Well, if you would be
more careful, I wouldn't potato
all the long legs from
the hidden spoon.
What just happened?
I believe the chip is installed
against his speech center.
Huh. Do it again.
The human brain is not
a plaything, Ms. Kean.
Please don't habituate
the curtain rod.
(chuckles)
And... ah.
Stay.
There. How does that feel?
(grunts)
Peter Piper picked a
peck of pickled peppers.
Oh, God. Thank you, Lucius.
LUCIUS: So what
exactly are we looking for?
Anything tying Walker or
Eduardo to the destruction of Haven.
Why would Walker
kill all those people?
That's what we have to find out.
Oh, yes.
It appears the chip
retains an audio log
of every verbal communication
with Nygma while he was under.
There's some damage, but...
if the command to
attack Haven is still here,
I can trace it back
to the computer
from which it originated.
It has to be Walker.
They won't be able to sweep
this under the rug anymore.
Are you out there, Jim?
What do you want?
We have someone here...
who wants to say hello.
THOMPKINS: J-Jim?
What's happening?
Lee?
We found the
Queen of the Narrows
in a run-down hidey-hole
on the north side. Tell me,
how many ex-fiancées
do you have, anyway?
Leave her out of this.
She's not involved.
Ah, but she's a criminal,
and all criminals in Gotham
are now under a death sentence.
But what happens
next is up to you.
A trade, perhaps.
Lee Thompkins for Ed Nygma.
Fine.
Good. Bring Nygma
to the GCPD now.
No, we meet at Haven.
I want you to see the
carnage you've caused.
Always so emotional.
That's not how
wars are won, Jim.
Those are my terms.
Take it or leave it.
(radio crackles)
Okay. I'll play your game.
What are you doing?
He's never gonna let
you walk out of there.
I don't recall volunteering
as a trading chit!
He doesn't want Ed.
He wants the chip.
So I'll give him
the chip. Bruce,
do you have any contacts
in the mainland press?
Several.
What would it take to broadcast
the information from the chip
- to the mainland?
- A transmitter, which I have,
and a very large
antenna, which I do not.
I know where there's an
antenna in the Green Zone,
but you're not gonna like it.
The roof of the GCPD.
(whispering): Lee.
- Harvey.
- Where the hell have you been?
You've been gone for months.
I don't know.
I can't remember anything.
What happened to me?
I don't know. We're
gonna figure it out.
I promise.
Let's go.
BULLOCK: It's gonna be okay.
(beeping, clicking)
GORDON (over radio):
Eduardo just arrived.
He brought backup, like
we expected. Time to move.
Copy that.
Let's go.
(birds squawking)
THOMPKINS: Jim!
Who are these people?
I'm gonna get you
out of here, Lee.
I'm not sure that's true, Jim.
It seems you forgot
to bring someone.
It's hard to make a swap
when you have nothing to trade.
We both know this is
really what you want.
Proof that you and
Walker are responsible
for the destruction of Haven
and the murder of
hundreds of innocent people.
Now let her go.
Let me guess, you made a copy
so you can do this little
bit of theatrics for me.
I expected more from you, Jim.
Three soldiers against
one man without a gun.
You sure you
brought enough help?
I don't need any help.
Is that why you sent
Nygma to do your dirty work?
So he could pick up
your slack like I used to?
Still dining out on pulling
me from that burning truck.
I carried more
than my fair share.
I was always the first man in.
Your recklessness
got people killed.
I don't know what the
hell you're talking about.
Ramirez?
No.
Johnson.
Bolton.
Their deaths were not on me.
Yeah.
Put a bullet in my mouth
and shut me up.
No.
Not a bullet.
But I am gonna shut your mouth.
Once and for all.
Come try.
(creaking)
You sure this is the place?
Yep.
This is the place.
Stop her!
Ouchie. You're quick.
I know you?
- Doubt it.
- Uh-huh.
You killed Jeremiah.
You're famous.
(laughs) Not so scary.
I could be famous.
You want a shot at me, too?
Unfortunately, you won't
have the opportunity.
Careful.
This is my workshop
where I make my boom-booms.
Anything here, boom,
boom. Then more boom
and more boom,
then the whole room...
- Boom, boom. We get it.
- You're bluffing.
Catch.
Ooh! No, no!
- (watch ticking)
- MAGPIE: Whoops!
(laughs) That watch
must have been an original,
but other stuff in
there, boom, boom.
Good luck.
We tie our shoelaces together,
then we lasso the
keys off the desk.
And then what, Roy Rogers,
huh? They surrender in awe?
No harebrained scheme
is gonna get us out of here.
Hello!
Hope you don't mind, I...
borrowed some cop
stuff from the garage.
Oh, boy, you can
put your guns down.
Kevlar in this thing is
designed to withstand a blast
that can tear down a
building twice this size.
What is that?
Is it not obvious?
It's a bomb!
Okay.
Let's play a game.
- Clear out.
- Ah, ah, ah, ah.
If anyone leaves this
building, this thing blows.
You gomers messed with
the wrong super genius,
and now it's time
for a little payback.
Nygma, you're a son of a bitch!
Oh, not now, Bullock.
The body count at Haven
wasn't big enough for you, huh?
Shut up!
What's your game?
The only way to
deactivate this bomb
is to put a four-digit
code on the keypad there.
What's the code?
(clears throat)
The pallid beach mouse can
give birth every four weeks.
Assuming we start
with two mice,
and that the size of an
average litter is 12 mice,
and that they are equally
split male to female,
how many pallid beach mice
would we have at
the end of one year?
The answer to that
question is the code.
Oh, I almost forgot.
- You have two minutes.
- (beeps)
After that, everyone
in here goes splat.
Except for me, of course.
(panting)
I'm in position.
Copy. Plug the recorder
to the transmitter.
Next, you'll connect the
transmitter to the radio.
There should be a black
box at the base of the antenna.
Let me know when
you get it open.
- Nygma's bomb ploy
won't last forever.
- We just have to
wait for the exhaust
fans to come to
a complete stop before
you can use the gas.
What are you doing?
(grunting and groaning)
(both grunting)
(both groaning)
You want to take
responsibility for people dying?
Look around.
This is all on you.
What the hell does that mean?
Walker spent months
trying to convince her
superiors that Gotham
was overrun by criminals.
We were this close
to being sent in
when you set up Haven.
The fact that one man was able
to safely house
and rescue hundreds
of innocent civilians showed
the military higher-ups
that the criminal
element of Gotham
must not be so big
and scary after all.
They were ready
to send in relief,
so it had to come down.
Why? What the
hell does she want?
They were innocent
people, children.
They were an acceptable
loss for the mission.
What mission, damn it?
(laughs)
That's enough.
(grunts)
Take her out back and shoot her.
He doesn't need to see this.
It's my gift to you,
a small mercy.
You never should have
brought her into this, Eduardo.
(groans)
Can we speed things
along, please, Mr. Fox?
The exhaust fans
have to wind down
before they can
change directions.
If you throw the canisters in
now, the gas will blow outside.
Bruce, status?
One second.
I'm here. The box is open.
LUCIUS: Two dark
green wires right in front.
Attach those to the transmitter.
The message will send.
(whirring, beeping)
It's done.
One minute left.
Everybody hear that?
One minute before
this thing explodes.
I know the answer.
Uh... (chuckles) Nope,
don't think you do, Bullock.
My high school zoology class
is still rattling around up here.
High school was a long time ago,
so let's just take the
full minute, shall we?
Really think about it.
I don't need to.
The pallid beach
mouse is extinct.
It disappeared in 1959.
The number you'll have at
the end of the year is zero.
The number is zero.
Trust me on this.
I got in trouble. I had to
write an essay about it.
I swear to God.
Oh, dear.
(indistinct chatter)
(groans)
I got a math problem for you.
- Count these bullets.
- (inhales)
Yes!
- (grunts)
- You want to know why
Ramirez and the
rest didn't make it out?
After your tour of duty was up,
we were caught
behind enemy lines,
taken to the darkest
hell on Earth...
Peña Duro.
Have you heard of it?
Prison? I didn't know.
No one did,
'cause it's where we were
left to die by our government.
I was the only
one that survived.
Walker...
Walker, she found
me in that place.
She pulled me out.
She gave me a new purpose.
She made you her killer.
No, no, Jim.
She's the killer.
And you have no idea.
- (gunshots)
- Lee?
You and your stupid revenge.
The diamond isn't even worth
anything in Gotham anyway.
Unless...
The diamond is worth
something on the mainland.
And I bet you have
way more where that came from.
You're leaving Gotham.
Congratulations,
you're a genius.
Why?
"Alexander the Great
"then looked upon his land
"and wept.
For there was nothing
left to conquer."
I've done all I can in Gotham.
Some things twice.
(chuckles lightly)
There's nothing left
for me here anymore.
I want in.
I can't even walk
around the city
without some lowlife
trying to take me out.
Just so he can up his cred.
I don't want to be the person
who killed Jeremiah Valeska.
I just want to be myself.
And I can't do that
in Gotham anymore.
My heart weeps for you.
But no.
- What if I could get us
out of here?
- (Oswald laughs)
You do that, I will cut you in.
50-50.
Ten percent, and
I won't murder you
- once we reach
the mainland.
- Deal.
Selina, wait!
She said, "Anything in
the room could be a bomb."
Not the room itself.
Did you know that
the whole time?
Just thought of it.
We should hurry before
she gets away
with all our stuff.
Don't worry.
She won't get far.
Alvarez, take Lee to my office.
Be right there.
I got to be honest
with you, man.
I don't know how many
more of these close calls
this old heart can take.
We were able to
transmit the audio logs,
but until I hear back
from my contacts,
I won't know if
they received them.
Well, if they did,
probably have a
lot of questions.
We'll spend the
night and help out.
Alfred, can you go back to the
apartment and grab what you can?
Certainly, Master Bruce.
Thanks, Bruce.
The next time I
get a short straw,
I'm just gonna
walk into traffic.
Where has Lee
been this whole time?
I don't know.
I'm not gonna wait around
to watch their touching reunion.
What is happening here?
I don't know where to start.
When I didn't hear from you,
I'd hoped you'd
gotten out of Gotham.
The last thing that I remember
is Jeremiah
destroying the bridges.
That was over three months ago.
Three months? Oh, my God.
You don't remember anything?
I'm trying, and...
Right before the
bridges came down,
you said you were
leaving the city.
Why didn't you?
I don't know, Jim.
None of this is
making any sense.
We're still cut off.
There's no help.
It's been hard.
Actually, that's not true.
It's been hell.
People needed hope,
so I put on a brave face.
Pretended I knew what to do.
But you know me, Lee.
I'm just a cop.
And now I'm really lost.
Hey, it's okay.
(distant siren)
We're here now.
We'll just try to put the
pieces back together again.
Maybe we can help each other.
Let's start with my memory.
I went back to the Narrows.
I saw Ed.
We fought. We...
Oh.
He stabbed me.
- What?
- Wait, let me
remember.
I stabbed him.
There was so much blood.
Then I was... (exhales)
somewhere...
A hospital, maybe?
- (scoffs)
- (man groans)
Eduardo. (clicks tongue)
So much potential,
but not quite up to the task.
- (beeping)
- Walker.
(case opens)
How?
We've been burned.
The press have recordings of me
instructing Nygma
to take down Haven.
I thought I might
accomplish my task
without setting
foot in this foul city,
but that's not to be.
- You won't die yet,
my warrior.
- (groaning)
There is so much
more for you to do.
Professor Strange will
have you fixed up in no time.
(device beeps, clicks)
(respirator powers up)
(sharp inhale)
(distorted): Jim Gordon.
Don't worry about Gordon.
Nygma was never alone.
There was a second operative.
(sharp inhale)
You okay?
You cold?
(brief whir)
The hospitals were
all out of commission.
Just the one clinic
in the green zone.
Lee?
Time to die, Jim Gordon.
(Jim grunting)
(both grunting)
- (electricity crackles)
- (exhales)
(owls hooting)
(faint clanging)
(leaves rustling)
♪♪
- (grunts, groans)
- Ah...
(thud)
Wanted: one butler.
Military background a plus.
References required.
Yes, Mr. Pennyworth.
I have a job for you.
(distant foghorn)
(rapid gasping)
SELINA: Well, you
weren't lying when you said
she wouldn't get far.
(dog panting)
Pretty crown's...
(chuckles) booby-trapped.
Ouch.
Ouch, indeed.
I couldn't have you
coming back here
and making off with
all of my belongings.
Our belongings.
Cut my wings, let me go?
Bang, bang.
- What the hell?
- (dog whines)
The buckshot in her gut
wasn't enough punishment?
Just a little reminder
of what happens
when people try
to steal from me.
(shuddering breath)
Good to know.
Partner.
(sirens wailing)
BULLOCK: So Lee has a chip, too?
GORDON: I don't know
how, but it seems that way.
Walker must have
been holding onto her
as some sort of plan
B this whole time.
Three months? That's a hell
of a long game she's playing.
Which means she probably
has other tricks up her sleeve.
(moans)
Hey.
(grunts)
- Welcome back.
- Oh, hell.
This is gonna keep happening.
What's wrong with me?
The good news is, I think
I can actually answer that.
- (exhales)
- (door opens)
BARBARA: Jim.
I need to talk to you.
Now is not a good time, Barbara.
Don't you remember the good
time we had the other night?
- Over there?
- Say what?
You need to leave now.
I'm pregnant.
Good to see you, Lee.
Long time.
Congratulations?
(buoy bell dinging)
(labored breathing)
You.
You're supposed
to be dead, mate.
Sorry to disappoint.
You hurt my boy...
and I will bite your face off.
(manic giggling)
(laughing): Yeah. Yeah.
Ah... Bruce will
be along shortly.
In the meantime...
This place is in desperate need
of some good,
old-fashioned butlering.
How did you even find a way
off the bloody island anyway?
How? One if by land,
two if by sea,
three if by digging a
tunnel under the river.
But enough questions.
Today is the big day.